Guide to the Women for Justice Records
University of Houston Libraries
Women for Justice Records
1971-1997
2008-002
Women for Justice; Howard, Rebecca
7.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The collection is organized in eleven series and housed in 6 boxes. Perhaps the most interesting aspect of the material is the correspondence between the inmates and the organization. The series are organizational material, administrative documents, Goree unit TDC, correction system: laws & conditions, volunteer program, client services, Christmas projects, external correspondence, published information and photographic materials.
Historical Note:
Women for Justice was a model program, which started in 1971 and gradually ended around 1997. The program, ran by women, became an independent organization in 1977 after originally being apart of the Women in Action’s Criminal Justice Division. It was dedicated to working with inmates, ex-offenders, all criminal justice agencies, Houston/Harris County Courts, and Goree State Prison.
The primary purpose of the program was to teach offenders to deal with the trauma of incarceration while they awaited trial or served short term sentences. Moreover, the organization strived to help inmates and offenders understand the court system as it pertained to them. The program tracked as many clients as possible so that they could be assisted in making future plans. Additionally, a community based Resource Center was established. Social services were provided to inmates, ex-offenders, parolees and their families in a non-threatening atmosphere by a group of citizen volunteers aptly named Volunteers in Action.
The services provided varied greatly. The Christmas project, which was conducted during the week of Christmas, provided inmates with donated socks, toiletries, apparel, etc. Job counseling was provided free of charge to help former inmates and parolees in search of employment. There were daily/weekly prison visitations/workshops given by Volunteers in Action. Women for Justice received financial support from numerous organizations and companies such as Shell Oil Company, Exxon U.S.A, and First Presbyterian Church. In addition, the M.D. Anderson Foundation donated a house, which allowed for the organization to effectively perform daily activities and operations.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Women for Justice
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Photographs
Topical Term:
Inmates of institutions; Jails -- Texas; Prisons -- Texas; Volunteer workers in corrections -- Texas
Acquisition Information:
Donated by Mrs. Rebecca Howard (with assistance from her daughter Beverly Huffman), 2008
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection is organized in eleven series and housed in 6 boxes. Perhaps the most interesting aspect of the material is the correspondence between the inmates and the organization. The series are organizational material, administrative documents, Goree unit TDC, correction system: laws & conditions, volunteer program, client services, Christmas projects, external correspondence, published information and photographic materials. Of special interest are inmate correspondence, program records and organizational information. These records document to some degree the deplorable conditions of Texas prison system during this era.
Detailed List of Contents
- Organizational Material
  Scope and Contents
  This section houses information regarding the organization from its inception in 1971. Organizational documents regarding “Women for Justice” are compiled together.
  - Early Steering Committee (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Projects and Proposals (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Guidelines (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Non-Profit Corporation Status for “Women for Justice” (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - “Women for Justice” Brochure-Draft (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Draft for Proposal, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Administrative Documents
  General Correspondence and organizational meetings and membership rosters and IRS information of the organization etc are available.
  - Annual Report, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors Rosters (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board Meetings (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Organizational Spiral Notebooks (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
  - General Business Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 16-35)
  - General Business Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 36-44)
  - Financial Statements and Auditor’s Reports (Box 2, Folder 45-47)
  - IRS, W-4 Returns (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Membership Rosters (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Volunteer Meetings (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Services Performed (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Membership Directories (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Program Structure (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Parole Board Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Program Reports (Box 2, Folder 55-61)
  - “Women in Action” Newsletters (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - “Criminal Justice Highlights” Newsletters (Box 2, Folder 63-64)
  - Criminal Justice Information System” Newsletters (Box 2, Folder 65)
- Goree Unit, TDC
  Goree Prison Unit visitation program is a very important part of the group and the apparel requests, stationary donations etc happened at regular intervals of time.
  - Goree Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 66-67)
  - Goree Programs, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Supply Requests, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Supply Requests, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 70)
- Correction System - Laws & Conditions
  The facts about the Texas Department of Corrections, jail reforms and various other information regarding the improvement of the prison system have been compiled together.
  - Jail Reforms and Renovations (Box 2, Folder 71-72)
  - Judge Carl Bue Court Order on Reorganization of Jails (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Jail Committee (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Statistics: Criminal Justice & Harris County (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Survey of Women inmates in Harris County Jail (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Texas Department of Corrections (TDC) Rules (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Rights of Arrested (Box 2, Folder 78-79)
  - Information/guides (Box 2, Folder 80-81)
  - D.C: Case Study of Children of women inmates (Box 2, Folder 82)
- Volunteer Program
  Training and recruitment of volunteers, volunteer meetings and various other workshops pertaining to the volunteers has been put together in this series.
  - Volunteers in Action (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Women in Action, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Training Material, 1971, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Training Material, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Training Material, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Training Material, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Volunteers for Probation Training, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Volunteer Communication (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Rules and Guidelines (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - General Meeting Volunteers, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - General Meeting Volunteers, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Volunteer Management Seminar (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Potential Volunteers, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - The art and science of helping (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Applications for Training, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Volunteer Recruitment and Support, 1975-76 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - National Volunteer Awards (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Job Description (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Volunteer Roster, 1975-76 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Volunteers Information (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Volunteer Record Sheets (Box 3, Folder 103-108)
- Client Services
  This series has a large collection of inmate letters and logs of the prison visitation by volunteers and logs about the donation of apparel to the inmates.
  - Resource Center Activities Record Book (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Inspirational Quotes (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Donated Apparel Logs (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Donated Apparel Logs (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Daily Logs, September 1979 (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Daily Logs, November 1979 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Daily Logs, February 1980 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Daily Logs, March 1980 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Daily Logs, April 1980 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Daily Logs, May 1980 (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Daily Logs, August 1980 (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Daily Logs, September 1980 (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Daily Logs, October 1980 (Box 3, Folder 121)
  - Daily Logs, December 1980 (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - Daily Logs, January 1981 (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Daily Logs, February 1981 (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - Daily Logs, March 1981 (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - Daily Logs, April 1981 (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Daily Logs, May 1981 (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - Daily Logs, June 1981 (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - Daily Logs, July 1981 (Box 3, Folder 129)
  - Daily Logs, August 1981 (Box 3, Folder 130)
  - Daily Logs, September 1981 (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - Daily Logs, October 1981 (Box 3, Folder 132)
  - Daily Logs, November 1981 (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - Daily Logs, December 1981 (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - Daily Logs, January 1982 (Box 3, Folder 135)
  - Daily Logs, February 1982 (Box 3, Folder 136)
  - Daily Logs, March 1982 (Box 3, Folder 137)
  - Daily Logs, April 1982 (Box 3, Folder 138)
  - Daily Logs, May 1982 (Box 3, Folder 139)
  - Daily Logs, June 1982 (Box 3, Folder 140)
  - Daily Logs, July 1982 (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - Daily Logs, August 1982 (Box 3, Folder 142)
  - Daily Logs, September 1982 (Box 3, Folder 143)
  - Daily Logs, October 1982 (Box 3, Folder 144)
  - Daily Logs, November 1982 (Box 3, Folder 145)
  - Daily Logs, December 1982 (Box 3, Folder 146)
  - Daily Logs, January 1983 (Box 3, Folder 147)
  - Daily Logs, February 1983 (Box 3, Folder 148)
  - Daily Logs, March 1983 (Box 3, Folder 149)
  - Daily Logs, April 1983 (Box 3, Folder 150)
  - Daily Logs, May 1983 (Box 4, Folder 151)
  - Daily Logs, June 1983 (Box 4, Folder 152)
  - Daily Logs, July 1983 (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - Daily Logs, August 1983 (Box 4, Folder 154)
  - Daily Logs, September 1983 (Box 4, Folder 155)
  - Daily Logs, October 1983 (Box 4, Folder 156)
  - Daily Logs, November 1983 (Box 4, Folder 157)
  - Daily Logs, December 1983 (Box 4, Folder 158)
  - Daily Logs, January 1984 (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Daily Logs, February 1984 (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - Daily Logs, March 1984 (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - Daily Logs, April 1984 (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - Daily Logs, May 1984 (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - Daily Logs, June 1984 (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Daily Logs, July 1984 (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Daily Logs, August 1984 (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - Daily Logs, September 1984 (Box 4, Folder 167)
  - Daily Logs, October 1984 (Box 4, Folder 168)
  - Daily Logs, November 1984 (Box 4, Folder 169)
  - Daily Logs, December 1984 (Box 4, Folder 170)
  - Daily Logs, January 1985 (Box 4, Folder 171)
  - Daily Logs, February 1985 (Box 4, Folder 172)
  - Daily Logs, May 1985 (Box 4, Folder 173)
  - Daily Logs, June 1985 (Box 4, Folder 174)
  - Daily Logs, July 1985 (Box 4, Folder 175)
  - Daily Logs, August 1985 (Box 4, Folder 176)
  - Daily Logs, September 1985 (Box 4, Folder 177)
  - Daily Logs, October 1985 (Box 4, Folder 178)
  - Daily Logs, November 1985 (Box 4, Folder 179)
  - Daily Logs, December 1985 (Box 4, Folder 180)
  - Daily Logs, January 1986 (Box 4, Folder 181)
  - Daily Logs, February 1986 (Box 4, Folder 182)
  - Daily Logs, March 1986 (Box 4, Folder 183)
  - Daily Logs, April 1986 (Box 4, Folder 184)
  - Daily Logs, May 1986 (Box 4, Folder 185)
  - Daily Logs, June 1986 (Box 4, Folder 186)
  - Daily Logs, July 1986 (Box 4, Folder 187)
  - Daily Logs, August 1986 (Box 4, Folder 188)
  - Daily Logs, September 1986 (Box 4, Folder 189)
  - Daily Logs, October 1986 (Box 4, Folder 190)
  - Daily Logs, November 1986 (Box 4, Folder 191)
  - Daily Logs, December 1986 (Box 4, Folder 192)
  - Daily Logs, January 1987 (Box 4, Folder 193)
  - Daily Logs, February 1987 (Box 4, Folder 194)
  - Daily Logs, March 1987 (Box 4, Folder 195)
  - Daily Logs, April 1987 (Box 4, Folder 196)
  - Daily Logs, May 1987 (Box 4, Folder 197)
  - Daily Logs, June 1987 (Box 4, Folder 198)
  - Daily Logs, July 1987 (Box 4, Folder 199)
  - Daily Logs, August 1987 (Box 4, Folder 200)
  - Daily Logs, September 1987 (Box 5, Folder 201)
  - Daily Logs, October 1987 (Box 5, Folder 202)
  - Daily Logs, November 1987 (Box 5, Folder 203)
  - Daily Logs, December 1987 (Box 5, Folder 204)
  - Daily Logs, January 1988 (Box 5, Folder 205)
  - Daily Logs, February 1988 (Box 5, Folder 206)
  - Daily Logs, March 1988 (Box 5, Folder 207)
  - Daily Logs, April 1988 (Box 5, Folder 208)
  - Daily Logs, May 1988 (Box 5, Folder 209)
  - Daily Logs, June 1988 (Box 5, Folder 210)
  - Daily Logs, July 1988 (Box 5, Folder 211)
  - Daily Logs, August 1988 (Box 5, Folder 212)
  - Daily Logs, September 1988 (Box 5, Folder 213)
  - Daily Logs, October 1988 (Box 5, Folder 214)
  - Daily Logs, November 1988 (Box 5, Folder 215)
  - Daily Logs, December 1988 (Box 5, Folder 216)
  - Daily Logs, January 1989 (Box 5, Folder 217)
  - Daily Logs, February 1989 (Box 5, Folder 218)
  - Daily Logs, March 1989 (Box 5, Folder 219)
  - Daily Logs, April 1989 (Box 5, Folder 220)
  - Daily Logs, May 1989 (Box 5, Folder 221)
  - Daily Logs, June 1989 (Box 5, Folder 222)
  - Daily Logs, July 1989 (Box 5, Folder 223)
  - Daily Logs, August 1989 (Box 5, Folder 224)
  - Daily Logs, September 1989 (Box 5, Folder 225)
  - Daily Logs, October 1989 (Box 5, Folder 226)
  - Daily Logs, November 1989 (Box 5, Folder 227)
  - Daily Logs, December 1989 (Box 5, Folder 228)
  - Daily Logs, December 1990 (Box 5, Folder 229)
  - Daily Logs, January 1994 (Box 5, Folder 230)
  - Daily Logs, December 1994 (Box 5, Folder 231)
  - Daily Logs, December 1995 (Box 5, Folder 232)
  - Commissary money requests (Box 5, Folder 233-234)
  - Legal Studies Clinic (Box 5, Folder 235)
  - Inspirational Verse (Box 5, Folder 236-237)
  - Inmate Letters (Box 5, Folder 238-242)
  - Inmate Letters (Box 6, Folder 243-262)
- Christmas Projects
  Christmas Project was one of the most important events during any calendar year. The inmates were given gifts and group events were held to get the joyous mood among the prisoners.
  - 1974 (Box 6, Folder 262)
  - 1976 (Box 6, Folder 263)
  - 1977 (Box 6, Folder 264)
  - 1978 (Box 6, Folder 265)
  - 1979 (Box 6, Folder 266)
  - 1980 (Box 6, Folder 267-268)
  - 1981 (Box 6, Folder 269)
  - 1984 (Box 6, Folder 270)
  - 1985 (Box 6, Folder 271-272)
  - 1986 (Box 6, Folder 273)
- External Correspondence
  This series holds the documents about the organizations and corporate donors who helped “Women for Justice” run the various programs of theirs by monetarily contributions or in any other form.
  - General
    - Speaking Engagements (Box 6, Folder 274)
    - Board of Corrections Appointment Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 275)
  - Donation Solicitation
    - Shell Oil Company (Box 6, Folder 276-277)
    - St. Albert’s Catholic Church (Box 6, Folder 278)
    - Price Waterhouse (Box 6, Folder 279)
    - New Convent Presbytery (Box 6, Folder 280)
    - M.D. Anderson Foundations (Box 6, Folder 281)
    - Exxon U.S.A (Box 7, Folder 282)
    - Synod of the Sun (Box 7, Folder 283)
    - Tenneco (Box 7, Folder 284)
    - Grace Presbytery Church (Box 7, Folder 285)
    - Hogg Foundation (Box 7, Folder 286)
    - First Presbyterian Church (Box 7, Folder 287)
    - Gulf Oil Company (Box 7, Folder 288)
    - Wheeler Avenue Baptist Church (Box 7, Folder 289)
    - Windwood Presbytery Church (Box 7, Folder 290)
    - First City National Bank (Box 7, Folder 291)
- Published Information
  Printed information about organizations or criminal justice information in general.
  - Pamphlets and Brochures (Box 7, Folder 292)
  - Greeting Cards (Box 7, Folder 293)
  - Clippings regarding Woman in Action/ Women for Justice (Box 7, Folder 294)
  - Clippings regarding Harris County Criminal Justice Information (Box 7, Folder 295)
  - Clippings regarding Texas Criminal Justice Information (Box 7, Folder 296)
  - Clippings regarding National Criminal Justice Information (Box 7, Folder 297)
- Photographic Materials
  Prints and slides of Women for Justice activities/volunteers.
  - Living Conditions (Box 7, Folder 298)
  - Visitation and Rap Session (Box 7, Folder 299)
  - Christmas Programs/Projects (Box 7, Folder 300)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs (Box 7, Folder 301)
  - Slides (Box 7, Folder 302)
- Memorabilia
  - Merriam-Webster Dictionary containing Contraband (Box 7, Folder 303)